Inventory of the James Barron Hope Papers (I) 1790-1965
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Papers of James Barron Hope, 1835-1963, n.d. (Box 1-2)
  - Box 2, 1872-1907, n.d. (Box-folder 2:1-139)
    - Committee of the Montefiore Literary and Social Association, Norfolk, Virginia, to Capt. James Barron Hope, Norfolk, 24 November 1884. (Box-folder 2:68)
      Appreciation for an address.
    - E. S. Gregory, Church of the Epiphany, Lynchburg, Virginia, to Capt. Jas. Barron Hope, Editor of The Landmark, Norfolk, Virginia, 1 December 1884. (Box-folder 2:69)
      He has written "a review of Miss Janey's forthcoming volume of Essays for the News. Enclosed is a sonnet "Ship-Wreck" by E. S. Gregory.
    - Aunt Mary [Blake], South Kensington, England, to James Barron Hope, Editor of The Landmark, Norfolk, Virginia, 12 December 1884. (Box-folder 2:70)
      Letter concerns a photo of a miniature of their grandfather [James Barron] and other family letters.
    - Jno. S. Tucker, Washington, D.C., to Capt. Jas. Barron Hope,2 January 1885. (Box-folder 2:71)
      Letter concerns the movement for Hope to be Collector of Customs.
    - Invitation to James Barron Hope for Inauguration Ceremonies, 4 March 1885. (Box-folder 2:72)
    - E. T. Powell, Norfolk, Virginia, to Capt. Jas. Barron Hope, Norfolk, 23 May 1885. (Box-folder 2:73)
      Appreciation of poem read publicly by Hope.
    - John Esten Cook, Boyce, Virginia, to Capt. Jas. Barron Hope,30 May 1885. (Box-folder 2:74)
      Letter concerns a contribution of an essay to The Landmark.
    - Geo. Fred'k. Holmes, University of Virginia, to Capt. Jas. Barron Hope, Norfolk. 30 May 1885. (Box-folder 2:75)
      Compliment on Hope's Memorial Poem, with some criticism of it.
    - Wm. F. Vilas, Office of Postmaster General, Washington, D.C., to James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia; 28 December 1885. (Box-folder 2:76)
      Acknowledgment of Hope's commendation of him and appreciation for the Centennial Ode of Hope.
    - Edward V. Valentine, Richmond, to James Barron Hope, Norfolk, 21 January 1886. (Box-folder 2:77)
    - Capt. James Barron Hope, "Extracts from Hammersly: 'Naval Encyclopedia,' under the heading, 'Navy Yard (Gasport) Norfolk, Virginia'," 18 April 1886., 6 pages. AV. (Box-folder 2:78)
    - Jno. Jameson, General Superintendent, Post Office Department, Washington, D.C., to Hon. Jno. Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 28 May 1886. (Box-folder 2:79)
      Request that a recommendation be made for Railway Postal Clerk.
    - V. Dabney, Middleburg, Loudoun County, Virginia, to James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 4 July 1886. (Box-folder 2:80)
      Letter concerns an article which appeared in The Landmark of Norfolk.
    - John Goode, Department of Justice, Washington, to Mr. [James Barron] Hope,14 July 1886. (Box-folder 2:81)
      "I thank you for your splendid vindication in The Landmark."
    - Wm. F. Vilas, Postmaster General, Washington, D.C. to James Barron Hope, 26 July 1886. (Box-folder 2:82)
      Expression of warm regard.
    - James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, to W. H. Ruffner, State Normal School, Farmville, Virginia; 28 September 1886. (Box-folder 2:83)
      Introduces his niece, Rosa Chisman.
      Covering note for this letter is listed below, 13 April 1905, Box-folder 2:83.
    - W. H. Ruffner, Lexington, to Col. [?], 13 April 1905. (Box-folder 2:83)
      Covering note for the above letter written on 28 September 1886, Box-folder 2:83.
    - Wm. F. Vilas, Postmaster General, Washington, D.C., to Jas. Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 27 November 1886. (Box-folder 2:84)
      Appreciation for "very complimentary notice of the Department."
    - J. B. C[ar]y, Richmond, Virginia, to Capt. James Barron Hope, Norfolk, 5 January 1887. (Box-folder 2:85)
      Request that Hope make the historical address at the Hampton Academy reunion.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to Janey, Mrs. R. A. Marr, Cape Charles City, Virginia, 8 June 1887., l2 pages. ads. C. (Box-folder 2:86)
      Letter concerns work as Superintendent of Schools; family matters. Includes sketches and doggerel poems.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope], Norfolk, Virginia, to Robert Marr, 15 June 1887., l2 pages. ads. (Box-folder 2:87)
      A "chatty" letter profusely illustrated with his sketches.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope], Norfolk, Virginia, to Mrs. Ro. A. Marr, Cape Charles City, E. S. of Virginia, 17 June 1887., l7 pages. ads. C. (Box-folder 2:88)
      "Poetry," family affairs, and 3 sketches.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to his daughter, Mrs. Ro. A. Marr, Cape Charles City, Virginia; 20 June 1887. (Box-folder 2:89)
      Letter concerns her brother Richard; a profusely illustrated family letter.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to Janey, Mrs. R. A. Marr, Cape Charles City, Virginia, 23 June [1887]. (Box-folder 2:90)
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope], Norfolk, Virginia, to Janey [Hope Marr],25 June 1887. (Box-folder 2:91)
      Letter concerns school activities and family affairs.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to his daughter, Mrs. Marr, [28 July 1887]. (Box-folder 2:92)
      Family letter with sketches.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to his son-in-law, R. Marr, 2 August 1887. (Box-folder 2:93)
    - "Papards" [James Barron Hope] to Robert A. Marr, 8 August 1887., 6 pages. ads. (Box-folder 2:94)
      Letter concerns school business, editorials, etc.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope], South Carolina Springs, to Janey, Mrs. J[ames] B[arron] H[ope] Marr, Nantucket, Massachusetts, 19 August 1887. (Box-folder 2:95)
      Letter concerns family affairs and 2 pages of sketches. Enclosed: 3 more sketches.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope], Sweet Chalybete, to "Dear children," Mrs. J[ames] B[arron] H[ope] Marr, Nantucket, Massachusetts, 18 August 1887., 6 pages. ads. C. Encl. (Box-folder 2:96)
      Family affairs with 4 pages of sketches.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to Janey, Mrs. R. A. Marr, Nantucket, Massachusetts, 20 August 1887. (Box-folder 2:97)
      Family affairs and sketches.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope], Sweet Chalybete, Virginia, to Jennie, Mrs. J[ames] B[arron] H[ope] Marr, Nantucket, Massachusetts, 21 August 1887. (Box-folder 2:98)
      Letter concerns pictures sent by Mr. Marr, Nannie and "Mama."
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope], Sweet Chalybete, Virginia, to Mrs. J[ames] B[arron] H[ope] Marr, Nantucket, Massachusetts, 23 August 1887. (Box-folder 2:99)
      Packing for leaving there.
    - Fitzhugh Lee, Richmond, to Jas. Barron Hope, Norfolk, 23 August 1887. (Box-folder 2:100)
      Request that Hope deliver a poem at the dedication of the Lee Monument.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope], Norfolk, Virginia, to Janey, Mrs. J[ames] B[arron] H[ope] Marr, West Tisbury, Massachusetts, 7 September 1887. (Box-folder 2:101)
      Much engrossed in work and poetry; wrote 12 verses, 12 stories, night before; two "specimen" verses included and description of the poem.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope], Norfolk, Virginia, to Mrs. R. A. Marr, West Tisbury, Massachsetts," 13 September 1887. (Box-folder 2:102)
      My poem is done...is to be delivered on the 27th"; newspaper notices of his work; labor troubles in Norfolk. Enclosure: sketches.
    - Invitation to J. Barron Hope for the Centennial Anniversary of the Framing of the Constitution, 15 September 1887. (Box-folder 2:103)
      Announcement of the program of the day.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to Janey [Marr],[1887]. (Box-folder 2:104)
      Family letter.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to Marr, [1887]., 10 pages. ads. (Box-folder 2:105)
      Family affairs; illustrated with sketches.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to [Janey Hope Marr], [1887]. (Box-folder 2:106)
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to Janey, [1887]. (Box-folder 2:107)
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to Janey, [1887]., 8 pages. ads. (Box-folder 2:108)
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to Janey, [1887]. (Box-folder 2:109)
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope], Sweet Chalybete Springs, Alleghany County, Virginia, to Janey, [1887]. (Box-folder 2:110)
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to Janey and Nannie, his daughters, n.d. (Box-folder 2:111)
    - 2 cards. n.d. (Box-folder 2:112)
    - Edward [?] to Mrs. Pendergast, n.d. (Box-folder 2:113)
      Letter concerns hope that James Barron Hope come north to fill the place of John R. Thompson on the Post; comments on a new play by Hope.
    - "Papa" [James Barron Hope] to his wife Annie, n.d. (Box-folder 2:114)
      Family affairs; endorsement from "Papa" to Janey.
    - Obituary of Mrs. Anne Wythe Whiting, written by James Barron Hope, n.d. (Box-folder 2:115)
    - H. S. McCandlish, Corresponding Secretary for the Virginia Democratic Association, Washington, D.C., to Mrs. James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 16 September 1887. (Box-folder 2:116)
      A resolution of regret and condolence at the news of the death of James Barron Hope.
    - Ro. W. Hughes, Richmond, to Richard H. Baker, Jr., [son-in-law of James Barron Hope], 16 September 1887. (Box-folder 2:117)
      Letter concerns shock at death of Hope.
    - Edward V. Valentine, Richmond, to Mrs. Annie B. Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 16 September 1887. (Box-folder 2:118)
      Sympathy at time of death of James Barron Hope.
    - Jno. S. Tucker, Washington, D.C., to Mrs. James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 18 September 1887. (Box-folder 2:119)
      Consolation on occasion of death of James Barron Hope.
    - F. B. Blake, London, England, to Mrs. James B. Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 21 September 1887. (Box-folder 2:120)
      Condolences from her cousin on the death of Hope.
    - W. Gordon McCabe, Staten Island, New York, to Mrs. James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 24 September 1887. (Box-folder 2:121)
      Letter concerns distress at. the newspaper announcement of the death of Hope.
    - John Goode, Washington, to Mrs. [James Barron] Hope, 24 September 1887. (Box-folder 2:122)
      Requests that poem in honor of Gen. Lee written by "your...lamented husband" should be read at the monument.
    - William Couper, Florence, Italy, to Mrs. Hope, 30 September 1887. (Box-folder 2:123)
      Endorsement: "Wm. Couper, The Sculptor." Sympathy at time of death of James Barron Hope.
    - Edward V. Valentine, Richmond, to Mrs. [Jane Hope] Marr,11 November 1887. (Box-folder 2:124)
      Appreciation for a book of poems which was received.
    - W. Gordon McCabe, Petersburg, to Mrs. Janey B. Hope Marr, Norfolk, Virginia, 16 November 1887. (Box-folder 2:125)
      Letter concerns "task confided in me," probably at funeral of James Barron Hope.
    - John B. Cary, Richmond, Virginia, to Dr. Thomas N. Page, City 12 February 1892. (Box-folder 2:126)
      Letter concerns an article by Thomas Nelson Page in Lippincott on Southern Literature, in which James Barron Hope was not mentioned.
    - Thos. Nelson Page, Richmond, Virginia, to Col. John B. Cary, Richmond, 19 February 1892. (Box-folder 2:127)
      In answer to Cary, Page states that he mentioned Capt. Hope in a previous article; appreciation for article written by daughter of Capt. Hope.
    - S. Bassett French, Manchester, Virginia, to S. S. Nottingham, The Landmark, Norfolk, Virginia, 29 April 1892. (Box-folder 2:128)
      Letter concerns a request, forwarded to Mrs. [Janey Hope] Marr for information about the life of her father, [James Barron Hope].
    - S. Bassett French, Manchester, Virginia, to Mrs. Jane Barron Hope Marr, 10 May 1892. (Box-folder 2:129)
      An appreciation of the person and character of her father [James Barron Hope], and discussion of the sketch of his life which he has requested.
    - R. E. Lee, Jr., Washington, D.C., to Col. Marr, VMI, Lexington, Virginia, 28 November 1892. (Box-folder 2:130)
      A request for a copy of the poem [by James Barron Hope] read at the unveiling of his grandfather's statue in Richmond.
    - G. Watson James, Richmond, Virginia, to Mrs. Janey Hope Marr, Lexington, Virginia, 16 December 1895. (Box-folder 2:131)
      Appreciation of the character and genius of her father [James Barron Hope].
    - F[rank] B. Blake, London, to his cousin Janey [Hope Marr],29 January 1896. (Box-folder 2:132)
      Acknowledgment and appreciation of the receipt of copies of "A Wreath of Virginia Bay Leaves."
    - Walter Neale, Neale Co., Publishers, Washington, D.C., to Mrs. Janey Hope Marr, Lexington, Virginia, 13 January 1900. (Box-folder 2:133)
      Request for an article on James Barron Hope for The Conservative Review, and plans for the publication of his complete works.
    - A. B. Jones, The Valentine Museum, Richmond, to Mrs. Janey Hope Marr, Lexington, Virginia, 30 January 1904. (Box-folder 2:134)
      Appreciation for the gift to the museum of the poem, "Memoriae Sacrum" by her father [James Barron Hope], and a letter written by James Barron Hope to Miss Campbell.
    - John Goode, Washington, D.C., to Mrs. [Janey Hope] Marr,[Lexington], Virginia, including remarks he made about James Barron Hope, "Poet Laureate of Virginia," 29 January 1904. (Box-folder 2:135)
    - Charles W. Kent, Library of Southern Literature, University of Virginia, to Mrs. Janie Hope Marr, Blacksburg, Virginia, 21 September 1907. (Box-folder 2:136)
      Letter concerns an article on the life of her father [James Barron Hope] with specimens of his work.
    - Charles W. Kent, Library of Southern Literature, to Janie Hope Marr, 18 October 1907. (Box-folder 2:136)
      Regret that she could not contribute the article on her father.
    - T. P. [James], Library of Southern Literature, to Janie Hope Marr, 4 December 1907. (Box-folder 2:136)
      Letter concerns selections of poems by James Barron Hope. to be included in the volume and permission to use them.
    - Mary Anne, Jackson, to Anne, 29 May [?]. (Box-folder 2:137)
      Letter concerns accommodations at Jackson and Salem; regards to Mrs. and Miss Hope.
    - Text of a speech by C[arter] S. H[arrison], James River, Virginia, n.d., 24 pages, first page missing. ADr. E. (Box-folder 2:138)
      Letter concerns the internal revenue, "an abomination that bears heavily upon us...born of the republican party"; the distillation of brandy and whiskey and the importance of grape culture to Virginia; the problem of colored men running for office; the "Whig" and the Bourbors; John S. Wise, Mahone, the Danville riots, George H. Thomas, John Sherman and Fitzhugh Lee.
    - Page 21 of a political article by Henry A. Wise, n.d. (Box-folder 2:139)
  Series 2: Certificates and Scrapbook
- Certificates and Scrapbooks, 1847-1883, n.d. (Box-folder 3:1-8)
  Certificates of James Barron Hope and two Scrapbooks collected by James Barron Hope and his daughter, Janey Barron Hope Marr.
  - Certificate that James Barron Hope has completed the course in Chemistry and History at William and Mary College, 4 July 1847. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Signed by Rd. Saunders, Pres., B. Tucker, John Millington and Ch. Minnegerode.
  - Certificate of Bachelor of Civil Law, awarded to James Barron Hope by the College and University of William and Mary, 4 July 1847. (Box-folder 3:2)
    Signed as above.
  - Commission of James Barron Hope as Second Lieutenant in the Virginia Militia, signed by John F. Wily, Lt. Gov. of Virginia, 8 April 1848. (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Certificate that James Barron Hope has completed the course in Political Economy and Modern History at William and Mary College, 13 July 1848. (Box-folder 3:4)
    Signed as above, plus Geo. Fred'k Holmes and Arch'd C. Peachy.
  - Certificate that James Barron Hope was the delegate from the 2nd District to the State Convention of the Democratic Party of Virginia, 31 May 1884. (Box-folder 3:5)
    Signed by H. Sheppard.
  - Photograph of the James Barron Hope monument in Elmwood, n.d. (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Scrapbook signed "Jane Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia;" 21 September 1883., 100 pages. AV. (Box-folder 3:7)
    Endorsements: "Scrap Book kept by Janey Barron Hope with clippings about her Father, James Barron Hope."
  - Scrapbook with newspaper clippings n.d., 100 pages. AV. (Box-folder 3:8)
    Endorsement: "Scrap Book of his early work kept by James Barron Hope. Afterwards added to by his daughter [Janey Barron Hope Marr], and with some of her published work added."
  Series 3: Literary and Artistic Works of James Barron Hope
- Literary and Artistic Work of James Barron Hope, 1864-1881, n.d. (Box-folder 4:1-40)
  Some of the literary and artistic work of James Barron Hope is collected in this box.
  - Poems by James Barron Hope, 1864-1881, n.d. (Box-folder 4:1-27)
    - Verses founded in the Trenches, footnote: In the Trenches before Petersburg,21 December 1864. (Box-folder 4:1)
      On reverse: sketch and signature James Barron Hope.
    - Poem - To Our Nannie, signed "Papa" [James Barron Hope], 5 March, 1881. (Box-folder 4:2)
      (Nannie was his daughter Anne Hope).
    - Poem - Leoni Di Monota; A Legend of Verona, Subtitle, I. The Mirror,[by James Barron Hope], n.d., 8 pages. Ams. (Box-folder 4:3)
    - Poem - Leoni Di Monota; A Legend of Verona,[by James Barron Hope], n.d., 10 pages, page 1 is missing. AMs. (Box-folder 4:4)
    - Poem - Leoni, Subtitled " Canto I-III," n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 4:5)
      - Poem - Leoni, Subtitled: Canto I, with sketches of characters, n.d., 6 pages. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Endorsed: "The property of Caroline Matilda Campbell, presented to her by her much-esteemed friend, the Author, James Barron Hope, Esq. of Hampton, Virginia"
      - Poem - Leoni, Subtitled: Canto II,n.d., 10 pages. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Endorsed as before, plus "The Original of 'Leoni Di Monota' given to me by the author in January 1854, while in Baltimore to deliver a lecture before the Maryland Institute."
      - Poem - Leoni, Subtitled: Canto III,n.d., l0 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 4:5)
        Endorsement. Letter concerns the ending, "G. M. C., 17th September, 1855."
    - Copy of The Bedouin of the Seas by James Barron Hope; Copy of The Star in the Heavens and Its Image on the Sea by James Barron Hope, n.d. (Box-folder 4:6)
      Endorsements: "The original manuscript of this was given to the Norfolk Library by his daughter, Mrs. Janey Hope Marr."
    - Poem - To My Wife,[by James Barron Hope], n.d., 4 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 4:7)
    - Poem - The Norsemen and the Roses,n.d. (Box-folder 4:8)
      Endorsement: "By Jas. Barron Hope."
    - Poem - Our Anglo-Saxon Tongue,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 4:9)
    - Poem - A King's Gratitude,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 4:10)
    - Poem - The Red Lord of the Sail,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 4:11)
    - Poem - Powhatan,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 4:12)
    - Poem - The Whippoorwill,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 4:13)
    - Poem - Unrewarded and forgotten,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 4:14)
      Endorsement: "Proof for Mr. Hope. Do not lose this I have no copy."
    - Poem - The Master of the World,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 4:15)
      Endorsement: "Written in 1886-7."
    - Poem in three parts, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 4:16)
      - Poem - Sir Walter Raleigh, I,n.d. (Box-folder 4:16)
        Endorsement: "Ms. of James Barron Hope's sonnet: 'Sir Walter Raleigh.' For Anne Whiting Marr from her mother."
      - Poem - Captain John Smith, II,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 4:16)
      - Poem - The Princess Pocahontas, III,[by James Barron Hope], n.d., AMs. (Box-folder 4:16)
    - Poem - Grey Bayard; An Ancient Story,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 4:17)
    - Poem - The Charge at Balakla Virginia,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 4:18)
      One verse only, with sketches.
    - Poem - A Story of the Caraccas Valley,[by James Barron Hope], n.d. (Box-folder 4:19)
      "Dedicated to Bayard E. Hand, Esq., U.S. Navy, by his old friend and former messmate."
    - Poem - First line: "Great Mother of Great Commonwealths," [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 6 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 4:20)
    - Poem - First line: "Mother of Commonwealths men call our State," [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 8 pages, page 6 missing. AMs. (Box-folder 4:21)
    - Poem - [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 4 pages. Fragments. AMs. (Box-folder 4:22)
    - Poem - [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 2 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 4:23)
    - Poem - [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 4 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 4:24)
    - Poem - First line: "For he felt the need of 'courage." [by James Barron Hope], n.d., Page 13 only. AMs. (Box-folder 4:25)
    - Poem, n.d., Pages 6, 7, 8 only. AMs. (Box-folder 4:26)
    - Poem, n.d., Page 22 only. AMs. (Box-folder 4:27)
  - Two stories, n.d. (Box-folder 4:28)
    Included on the backs of some pages are the author's sketches of some of the characters, [by James Barron Hope].
    - "Sick List Stories." n.d., 54 pages. (Box-folder 4:28)
      Chapter I. 22 pages.
      Chapter II. 11 pages.
      Chapter III. 2l pages.
    - "A Short and Confidential Letter" addressed "Dear Reader." n.d., 8 pages. (Box-folder 4:28)
  - Destiny, a Melodrama in Three Acts, by James Barron Hope, Hampton, Virginia, n.d., ll5 pages. AV. (Box-folder 4:29)
    "Scene laid in Germany, Costumes those of the Sixteenth Century.-Time: the reign of Charles 5th."
  - Notes on a play [Destiny, by James Barron Hope], n.d., l4 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 4:30)
  - An address [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 32 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 4:31)
    Subheadings: "Scriptorium" and "The Modern Newspapers." Last two pages are a poem which begins: "Ah! here it is! I'm famous now!...It really is in print."
    Second copy, without the poem. 28 pages.
  - The Crab Claw Gazette, dated Hampton,"Editors, Dr. William B. Vaughan, Capt. William I. Morissetti," 15 April 1856. (Box-folder 4:32)
    Endorsement: "Given to me by the Author, J[ames] B[arrron] Hope, September 1, 1856."
  - Address or editorial [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 4 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 4:33)
    Begins: "To arrive at correct conclusions concerning the impulses which prompted and the principles which governed the careers of famous men...."
  - Lecture on Hampton in the Revolutionary War [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 5 pages. AMs. (Box-folder 4:34)
  - Notes [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 11 pages, numbered from 19. AMs. (Box-folder 4:35)
    Notes on Governor Yeardley, Dr. John Pott, Nathaniel Basse, Benjamin Symes, John Utie, Richard Downes, Elizabeth Rolfe, Glass and Salt Makers, Daniel Gookin and Sir William Newce.
  - An article [by James Barron Hope], n.d., 28 pages, numbered 9 to 37. Incomplete. AMs. (Box-folder 4:36)
    The Ms. begins in the middle of a sentence: "the expedition settled on Roanoke Island...."
  - Copyright Certificates, 1874-1881. (Box-folder 4:37-39)
    - Copyright certificate for: Cotton Port Map: Showing movements of Cotton at Interior Towns and Ports from 1st September to 31st August, by James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 10 August 1874., PADS. (Box-folder 4:37)
    - Copyright certificate for: Sketches of North Carolina by Ex-Governor Vance, by James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 24 September 1874., PADS. (Box-folder 4:37)
    - Copyright certificate for: A few passages from the life of a Distinguished Virginian by Thomas Jefferson Rufflestimp, by James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 12 November 1874., PADS. C. (Box-folder 4:37)
    - Copyright certificate for: Under the Empire; or the Story of Madelon, by James Barron Hope, Norfolk, Virginia, 4 March 1878., PADS. C. (Box-folder 4:38)
    - Copyright certificate for: Arms and the Man; A Metrical Address recited at the Hundredth Anniversary of the Surrender of Lord Cornwallis at Yorktown, by James Barron Hope, 21 November 1881., PADS. (Box-folder 4:39)
  - Sketches by James Barron Hope, n.d., 33 items. (Box-folder 4:40)
  Series 4: Newspaper and Periodical articles written by or concerning James Barron Hope